Heritage Preservation Commission Collection
University of Minnesota Libraries
Heritage Preservation Commission Collection
1966 1994
University of Minnesota Northwest Architectural Archives, Manuscripts Division. [naa]
Heritage Preservation Commission (Minneapolis, MN)
3 drawings
12 cubic feet
This collection consists of prints of architectural drawings, generally not of the original construction, for buildings either designated or under consideration for historic designation at one time by the Heritage Preservation Commission of Minneapolis, MN. Buildings represented here include warehouses, churches, residences and other structures.
N213
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open to the public for research use.
Acquisition
The collection was donated by the staff of the Heritage Preservation Commission, Minneapolis, MN in 2003.
Arrangement
The collection is organized alphabetically by commission name.
Historical Note
The Minneapolis Heritage Preservation Commission (HPC) was formed in 1972 to serve as a citizen advisory body to the Minneapolis City Council. The Commission holds public hearings on matters related to preservation twice each month. These meetings are specifically held so that the commission can hear from the public on matters related to heritage preservation. The HPC evaluates the historical significance of buildings and districts and recommends buildings or districts to the City Council for designation as local landmarks.
In addition, the HPC reviews all building, demolition, moving, and sign permits for designated buildings and districts and prepares and administers design guidelines for reviewing repair, rehabilitation, new construction and demolition requests within historic districts. During this phase of the process the HPC requires architects and contractors to submit full working drawings for any changes and the plans in this collection were submitted to the HPC for this type of review.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of 37 sets of working drawings (prints rather than originals) for designated historic buildings (or buildings within historic districts) being renovated, remodeled or altered. These architectural drawings date from 1966 to 1994 and illustrate a wide variety of structures, including the "Frederick Cupola House", "Nicollet Island Homes", the warehouse (originally designed by Cass Gilbert) for the Theatre de la Jeune Lune and the remodeling of the Ribnick Furs store, among others. Architects represented here include the Architectural Alliance, Arvid Elness Architects, Ellerbe Becket Inc., and Cunningham Architects along with many others.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of the University of Minnesota Libraries. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Detailed Contents
The following section contains a detailed list of the materials in the collection.
- 163 East Island Avenue, 1991
  residence
  Roark Kramer Roscoe Design
  Minneapolis, MN
  blueline
- 2013 Stevens Avenue, 1988
  Whittier Alliance
- 2nd Street North Interceptor Soil Profile, 1966-69
  sewer
  photostats
- 400 Clifton Ave Expansion, 1989
  comm. #100
  Architectural Alliance
- Blind Inc., 1994
  remodeling
  job #94-06
  Houwman Design
- Ceresota Elevator, 1986
  grain elevator
  Ellerbe Associates
  blackline
- Colonial Warehouse, 1991
  warehouse
  212 3rd Ave North
- Colwell Building, 1990
  comm. #319
  Heise Reinen Macrae Associates
- Convention Center District skyways, 1991
  skyways
  comm. #9164
  Van Doren Hazard Stallings Inc.
- Cutter Residence reconstruction, 1992
  Sigma Phi Epsilon Fraternity
  comm. #9268
  Wells Woodburn O'Neil
- Dania Hall, 1991
  roof reconstruction
  comm. #91397.00
  Bakke Kopp Ballou & McFarlin Inc.
- Elliot Park IV Elm Building, 1989
  Arvid Elness Architects
- Federal Reserve Bank Minneapolis, 1994-95
  bank
  Project #92-381-001
  Walsh Bishop Associates, Inc.
- Frederick Cupola House, 1992
  2400 Fourth Avenue South
  Roark-Kramer-Roscoe
- Frisch Center, 1990
  comm. #89650
  Paul Pink and Associates Inc.
  xerox
- Gaviidae Common, 1988
  shopping center
  Cesar Pelli & Associates
- Heritage Exterior Improvements, 1990
  Dovolis Johnson & Ruggieri Inc.
- Its Greek to Me, 1990
  restaurant expansion & remodeling
  Dovolis Johnson & Ruggieri
- LaSalle Plaza, 1990
  high-rise building
  comm. #8541-887
  Ellerbe Becket Inc.
- Longfellow House, 1994
  comm. #9322
  Kodet Architectural Group
- Maceachron-O'Driscoll Residence, 1990
  Nicollet Island Restoration & Development Co.
- Manildra Milling Co., 1990
  comm. #9048
  Simons-Conkey, Inc.
- Market Hotel, 1988
  hotel
  Cuningham Architects P.A.
- Minneapolis Institute of Arts, 1990
  new arts storage, office, & future gallery
  Walsh Bishop Associates
- Minneapolis Institute of Arts, 1990
  new arts storage, office & future gallery addition
- Minneapolis State Theater, 1991
  theater restoration
  comm. #1749
  A.T. Heinsbergen & Company Inc.
- Minnesota Dept. of Transportation, 1993
  restoration of J.J. Hill Stone Arch Bridge
  A.G. Lichtenstein & Associates, Inc
  photocopy
- Nicollet Island Homes, 1987
  residences
  Reg #4979
  Miller Dunwiddie Architects Inc.
- Nicollet Mall Extension, 1991
  street
  BRW Architects Inc.
- Pillsbury Company General Offices, 1989
  office
- Powderhorn Assisted Living Residence, 1990
  comm. #84030
  Armstrong, Torseth, Skold, and Rydeen Inc.
- Public Storage Inc., 1988
  renovation of Minneaplis van and warehouse
  comm. #88-01-3017-01
  Korsunsky Krank Erickson
- Ribnick Furs, 1988
  store remodeling and addition
  comm. #1135.01
  Boarman & Associates
  blueline, xerox
- State Theater, 1990
  theater renovation
  Ellerbe Becket
- Studio One Lofts, 1988
  comm. #88.01.3008.01
- Swinford, The, 1990
  townhouses & apts
  comm. #8917
  Bowers Bryan Feidt
- Theater de la Jeune Lune, 1991-92
  comm. #89234
  Arvid Elness Architects Inc.